Boker tov, today's דף daf is ע"ח, Ayin Chet, 78, and we
are continuing in the middle of a little bit of a digression
here about when the Torah talks about שה, seh, does it meant
to exclude כלאים, kilayim, a hybrid? I mean, we got into it
because the question is if somebody were to steal a hybrid sheep
and goat, would they pay four and five if they were to
slaughter it, and the answer is that they would not, I mean
excuse me, that they would. Wait, I keep on... sorry, that they
would. I got that wrong, because it says או שה, o seh,
או o to include כלאים. kilayim. And then we said about the
או o by the שה seh by the קרבנות korbanot is to
exclude כלאים. kilayim. Not only are we excluding כלאים, kilayim, hybrid, we're
even excluding נדמה, nidmeh, something that looks... doesn't look like the parent.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara is going to be asking, okay,
fine, one case you have an או o to include, one case
you have an או o to exclude, but רבא Rava made a
statement that anytime it says שה, seh, it means to exclude כלאים.
kilayim. Here it sounds like we don't have that as a default,
like we either have to go, you know, have a פסוק pasuk
tell me one way or the other, but it's not clear what
the default is. So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to
turn to here. Let's take a look before we'll deal with that
a little bit here before we turn back to issues about גניבה.
geneivah. So the גמרא Gemara in ע"ח עמוד א' Ayin Chet Amud
Aleph says the following... אלא, ella, it's about
1, 2,
3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9 lines down by the asterisk...
asterisk second word in the line. אלא הא דאמר רבא, Ella ha
d'amar Rava, that which רבא Rava said, זה בניין אב, zeh binyan
av, this is a paradigm.
כל מקום שנאמר שה אינו אלא להוציא את הכלאים. Kol makom she'neemar
seh eino ela l'hotzi et hakilayim. The meaning is to exclude כלאים,
kilayim, wherever it says it. So the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to do,
you know, basically say, we're going to... גמרא'ס Gemara's going to find
one case where this statement is relevant, you know, wherever the Torah
says שה seh to exclude
כלאים. kilayim. So the גמרא Gemara says, להוציא את הכלאים. l'hotzi et
hakilayim. So the גמרא Gemara says, למאי הלכתא? l'mai hilchata? When is
that ever relevant? What הלכה halacha is that relevant for? אי לקדשים,
ee l'kodshim, if it's to tell me that you can't bring a
קרבן korban from an animal that's a hybrid, פשיטא היא, p'shita hee,
it's explicit, or I don't know if explicit, but explicit based through
the lens of the דרשות drashot of חז"ל. Chazal. שור או כשב,
shor o chesev, an ox or a lamb. The או o is
פרט להוציא, p'rat l'hotzi, that excludes כלאים. kilayim.
So not disagreeing with the law, כלאים kilayim is excluded, but it's
not based on the use of the word שה, seh, it's based
on the extra use of the או. o. אי למעשר, ee l'maaser,
if to tell me for מעשר בהמה, maaser behemah, you know, that
your new lamb and calves that are born you have to give
every
tenth, so תחת תחת יליף מקדשים. tachas tachas yaleef mi'kodshim. There's a
גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah, תחת השבט tachas hashevet that it learns from
קדשים. kodshim. So if by קדשים kodshim because of the או o
we excluded it, we exclude it by מעשר. maaser. By the way,
רש"י Rashi points out that it doesn't even say the word שה
seh by מעשר, maaser, it says the word צאן. tson.
That's what it's all... it's all your cattle and goats, right?
Yes, but not a כלאים. kilayim. Isn't he one of them? No,
that's the interesting point. You're right. Meaning now, of course, I don't
know why you're so shocked since the idea of מעשר maaser is
to be brought as a קרבן, korban, and if you can't have
a כלאים kilayim as a קרבן, korban, it makes sense that you
can't have a כלאים kilayim for this, right?
But anyway, but you're right, meaning something that's not about its unique
identity. On the other hand, look, something that's like an עולה olah
also, there's not a different הלכה halacha for a sheep or a
goat, well there is a הלכה halacha about I guess the נסכים,
neshachim, but anyway, but nevertheless, the point is but what you make
is a correct point that it's not just something like, you know,
by four and five, it's the irony, by four and five the
Torah actually makes a distinction between what type of an animal it
is, right? By a שור shor it's five and by a שה
seh it's four. And there we include כלאים. kilayim. By קרבנות korbanot
and מעשר maaser etc. for mostly it's like any of these animals
is okay but we exclude כלאים. kilayim. But yes, we do it
by מעשר maaser because you know ultimately מעשר'ס maaser's supposed to be
brought as a קרבן. korban. אי בבכור, ee b'bechor, if for the
issue of the firstborn animal, also to be brought as a קרבן
korban if it doesn't have a blemish, העברה העברה יליף ממעשר. havara
havara yaleef mi'maaser. We learn that from מעשר. maaser. כל אשר יעבר
תחת השבט kol asher yaavor tachas hashevet it says by מעשר, maaser,
by בכור bechor it says והעברת כל פטר רחם. vehaavarta kol peter
rechem. So again the הלכה halacha is true but it's not based
on רבא'ס Rava's דרשה. drasha. אינמי
נדמה אמרת לא, eenami nidmeh amarta lo, אינמי eenami or another way
to prove that by a בכור bechor we don't need רבא'ס Rava's
דרשה drasha is נדמה אמרת לא, nidmeh amarta lo, we already know
that you can't bring a נדמה nidmeh for a בכור. bechor. נדמה
nidmeh is an animal that both of its parents are of the
same species but it just looks like a different type of an
animal. It's the other way around, like a different species but it
looks like a שור, shor, right?
You can't bring that either then.
Right, well that would also be a נדמה, nidmeh, it just doesn't
look like its parent. אינמי נדמה לא, eenami nidmeh lo, if we
already know from that דרשה drasha to exclude even something that looks
different. דכתיב, dechseev, how do you know you can't bring that as
a בכור? bechor? אך בכור שור, ach bechor shor, however the firstborn
of an ox, so the דרשה drasha is עד שיהא שור ובכורו
שור. ad shey'hei shor u'bechoro shor.
By describing it as בכור שור, bechor shor, it emphasizes somehow that
it looks like the spitting image of the father, it looks like
its parent. Okay, so until it looks just like its parent.
so כלאים מיבעיא? kilayim mibaiya? Of course we would exclude
כלאים. kilayim. So it's true about all these קדשים kodshim related things,
but it's not based on the word שה. seh. So where do
you need רבא? Rava? אלא כי איתמא דרבא לעניין פטר חמור. ela
ki itma derava linyan peter chamor.
Okay, for what רבא Rava you need it for is for the
firstborn of a donkey and not now, not to tell you that
the donkey has to look, has to not be a hybrid donkey,
but to tell you what you can transfer the קדושה kedusha to,
because you're פודה podeh a פטר חמור. peter chamor. כדתנן, kidtnan, like
we taught in the משנה, mishna, אין פודין לא בעגל ולא בחיה.
ein podin lo be'egel velo bechaya. You cannot redeem a חמור chamor
on a שה. seh. Okay, right? It says פטר חמור תפדה בשה.
peter chamor tifdeh beseh. So there's that word שה. seh. Okay, so
it has to be a sheep, not a calf. ולא בחיה, velo
bechaya, obviously not in some type of a wild animal like a
deer or something. ולא בשחוטה, velo beshchuta, not a slaughtered sheep. You
can't say, oh, it's a sheep, it's just dead. No, sheep means
alive. שה ולא בטריפה, seh velo betrefah, or sheep that's a טריפה.
trefah. That's interesting. Okay, because presumably that can't be brought as a
קרבן. korban. ולא. velo. I wonder if you did do it and
then you found out and you didn't realize it was a טריפה
trefah and then you found out that it was, what the הלכה
halacha would be. ולא בכלאים. velo bechilayim. And here's our point, not
in a crossbreed even if it's a crossbreed between a sheep and
a goat. ולא בכוי. velo bechoy. And not a כוי, koy, which
is some type of a crossbreed of a sheep and a, I
forget what it is, a sheep and I don't even know. A
goat and a deer. Okay, a goat and a deer.
יש פרק שלם במשנה. yesh perek shalem bamishna.
I'm sure there is
from Rabbi Slifkin.
Okay, excellent.
Anyway, ולרבי אליעזר דמטבי ביה קרא. ulerabbi eliezer dematbi beih kra. Now,
fine, so that's our answer. So when רבא Rava says in the
entire תורה, Torah, שה seh means to exclude כלאים, kilayim, he means
the one time the תורה Torah says שה seh by redeeming a
פטר חמור. peter chamor. We don't have that based on anything else
and that we know to exclude כלאים kilayim because of the use
of the word שה. seh. Yes, David?
If it's a hybrid from a domesticated animal and an undomesticated animal,
i.e., a goat and a deer, yes, that's רש״י.
rashi. Right, right.
Okay, ולרבי אליעזר דמטבי ביה קרא, ulerabbi eliezer dematbi beih kra, now
one minute says the גמרא, gemara, that's not going to explain רבי
אליעזר rabbi eliezer because רבי אליעזר rabbi eliezer allows you to redeem
a בכור, bechor, a פטר חמור peter chamor on כלאים. kilayim. דתנן
רבי אליעזר מטבי בכלאים. detnan rabbi eliezer matbi bechilayim. מפני שהוא שה.
mipnei shehu seh. Yes,
it still is a שה, seh, says generic enough. So if it's
a crossbreed between a sheep and a goat, for him that would
still be under the generic title שה, seh, even though it's not
distinctively one species or another. Okay, but that's still like a lamb
of sorts, so for him you can do it. So we're back
to the question, what does שה seh exclude for רבא? Rava? Where
does שה seh come to exclude כלאים? kilayim? אלא כי איתמא דרבא,
ela ki itma derava, so where would רבא's Rava law be relevant
for רבי אליעזר? rabbi eliezer? לטעמיה
כי איתמא דרבא לטעמיה שנולד מן הטהור ועיבורו מן הטמא. letaameih ki
itma derava letaameih shenolad min hatahor ve'iburo min hatamei. Let's say you
have an animal that is an offspring, טמא tamei here means non-kosher
animal, an animal that's an offspring of a kosher mother and a
non-kosher father. Now, how any of this is possible, the גמרא's gemara
going to ask in a minute, but just to hear how רש״י
rashi describes it, the גמרא gemara in a minute's going to say
this is impossible, רש״י rashi says, לטעמיה שנולד מן הטהור. letaameih shenolad
min hatahor. רש״י rashi says,
פרה שילדה סוס parah sheyaldah sus ואביו סוס. ve'aviv sus. So a
cow mated with a horse and gave birth to a horse-looking animal.
או רחל שילדה חזיר o rachel sheyaldah chazir ואביו חזיר. ve'aviv chazir.
A ewe mated with a pig and gave birth to a baby
pig. Okay, so that would be a כלאים kilayim that would not
be permissible to be eaten. Now, you would think that that has
a lot more to do, a lot less to do with the
use of the word שה seh and just the fact that it's
hybrid and has to do with the fact that one of its
parents is non-kosher. That's the essence of it being אסור, asur, right?
Hybrid normally, the sense is it's not like a pure breed, you
know, and even if it came from other things that are okay
within the category, right? That's what Mike was asking before, like you
could have a sheep and a goat, both of which you could
bring as a קרבן, korban, but the offspring of the two you
can't bring as a קרבן korban because there's some separate concept of
being purebred. The שה, seh, right? As opposed to here it's like
the problem isn't that it's not purebred. The problem is that one
of its parents, even if this were biologically possible, is not kosher.
Okay, but that's what the גמרא's gemara saying, that's where שה seh
comes to exclude the offspring of a kosher and a non-kosher animal.
Okay? שנולד מן הטהור ועיבורו מן הטמא, shenolad min hatahor ve'iburo min
hatamei, it became pregnant from a non-kosher animal. ודלא כרבי יהושע. udela
kerabbi yehoshua. And not like רבי יהושע, rabbi yehoshua, meaning not like
רבי יהושע rabbi yehoshua necessarily disagree with this, although there's a long
תוספות tosafot to figure out whether רבי יהושע rabbi yehoshua agrees or
disagrees, but at least רבי יהושע rabbi yehoshua would learn it from
a different פסוק. pasuk. דאי רבי יהושע, de'ei rabbi yehoshua, רבי יהושע
rabbi yehoshua would learn how to exclude such an animal משה כשבים
ושה עזים. misey kshavim vesey izim. It says that you can eat,
you know, something, the sheep of a, by the way, there's the
use of the word שה seh both by a sheep and a
goat, which gets back to the point of, let's just stop a
minute and pull back for a minute and remember רבי אליעזר's rabbi
eliezer point a minute ago, which is why you can redeem a
פטר חמור peter chamor on a hybrid sheep and goat because the
תורה torah uses the word, the same way the use of the
word גדי gedi can be used for גדי עזים gedi izim and
a גדי, gedi, you know,
can be used for a sheep and a goat. שה seh can
be used for sheep and goat. שה כשבים ושה עזים. sey kshavim
vesey izim. And that's why by the way, right, when you have
a hybrid sheep and goat, we פסקן, pasken, getting back to גניבה
g'neiva for a minute, that you pay four and five, because since
the תורה Torah says או שה, oh seh, so שה seh would
include sheep and goat and it would include a hybrid sheep and
goat. Okay, so שה seh could include sheep or goat and according
in sometimes even a hybrid. Okay, but how do we know here
that so the I'm just you have this פסוק pasuk שה כשבים
ושה עזים. seh ksavim v'seh izim. But here he says from here
you also learn though that both parents have to be kosher parents
because it's use of the word plural. It's not שה כבש, seh
keves, it's not שה עז, seh ez, right, it is בכור שור,
bechor shor, that's singular, but כשבים ksavim means of sheep, both parents
were sheep. עזים, izim, both parents were goats. So only an animal
that is an offspring of two of of two kosher animals is
kosher. If one of the animals is not kosher, the child is
also not kosher. Okay, so he does not use learn it from
the word שה, seh, he learns it from the word כשבים ksavim
and עזים, izim, both parents have to be kosher.
So I know, but then you should learn that both parents have
to be the same thing.
I know, but he's not. What can I tell you? But he's
not. Okay, so he learns it from that פסוק, pasuk, so we're
back to the question. What does שה seh when case does שה
seh exclude כלאים? kilayim? Either it excludes כלאים kilayim from פטר חמור,
petter chamor, but that's not true according to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer.
So it excludes כלאים kilayim from if one animal is not kosher
that the offspring is not kosher. Well, that's a true הלכה halacha
but רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua learns it from a different פסוק pasuk
from שה כשבים ושה עזים. seh ksavim v'seh izim. Okay, עד שאביו
כבש ואמו כבשה. ad she'aviv keves v'imo kivsa. Okay,
so fine, but the גמרא Gemara somehow is not bothered with that.
That doesn't work for רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, but one way or
the other שה seh excludes כלאים. kilayim. It either excludes it from
פטר חמור petter chamor or it excludes it from a non-kosher parent,
okay, although the idea of a non-kosher parent could be learned from
a different פסוק pasuk as well. Now the גמרא Gemara says the
following: וטהורה מטמאה מי מעברה? v'tehorah mitmeiah mi me'abra? Really? Can a
kosher animal become pregnant from a non-kosher animal? I mean, you know,
those are like really that's real crossbreeding there. How would that happen?
אין, in, yes, דקיימא לן דאיעבר מקלוט כרבי שמעון. d'kayma lan d'iyaber
miklut k'Rabbi Shimon. So now there's a long רש״י Rashi here for
these four words. So...
yeah. So it says it can become pregnant from a from a
fused hoof animal like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. What does this mean?
So the question is, if two animals, kosher animals get together, what?
Right. So the פסוק pasuk says, you know, don't eat a camel,
don't eat a camel twice. So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says the
פסוק pasuk is coming to tell you is that even if you
have two cows that gave birth to an animal that's a little
bit like a camel. What does it mean it's a little bit
like a camel? It is a cow. But it happens to be
that its hooves are fused. Now wait a
minute, a camel
has split... does a camel have split hooves or fused hooves? את
הגמל כי מעלה גרה
הוא ופרסה לא הפריס.
et hagamal ki ma'aleh gerah
hu u'farsah lo hifris.
Right, its hooves are fused. So if, so רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says the reason the פסוק pasuk repeats don't eat a camel is
to tell you, even if an animal is born from a cow,
two cow, a cow and an ox, okay, it is a kosher
animal genetically, but it looks like a camel in that its hooves
are fused, that nevertheless is not kosher. That's what רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says. According to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, it's not kosher. Now,
okay,
that animal could mate with a cow, because we all know it's
really a cow. Okay, so that would be a case where you
could have a non-kosher animal mating with a kosher one and they
could actually mate. Right? Because it's really just not kosher because it's
got fused hooves, but it really is a cow. So the offspring
is also not kosher and that we learn out from this דרשה,
drasha, okay, that it's only when both parents are kosher. So you're
right, something that really is a non-kosher animal genetically or whatever, you
could never have that reality that it could produce an offspring with
a kosher animal. But two things that are genetically kosher but one
is not kosher because it has fused hooves, that could produce an
offspring and this פסוק pasuk tells us that the offspring is also
not kosher, either with the use of the word שה seh or
the use of the word כשבים. ksavim. All right, now we are
thankfully done with that discussion. Okay, so now we understand why שה
seh sometimes comes to exclude כלאים. kilayim. Back to the גמרא. Gemara.
It would be kosher and you could eat it?
They would say yes, yes. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. בעי רבא, ba'ei Rava, Rava says, הרי עלי עולה. harei
alai olah. Now, back to this question about גניבה g'neiva but now
specifically a question about being גונב קדשים. gonev kodshim. Remember we discussed
that if you're גונב קדשים gonev kodshim that the owner is חייב
באחריות, chayav b'achrayut, has a vow,
and because of the vow if they lose their קרבן korban they're
going to have to replace it. So then it's like it belongs
to the owner and you have to pay the owner the principal
and כפל kefel according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon even ד׳ וה׳
dalet v'hei because you basically have taken something that is of value
to the owner even though it's קדשים. kodshim. Okay, so now רבא
Rava has a really interesting question. Somebody took a vow, הרי עלי
עולה, harei alai olah, והפריש שור v'hifrish shor and he separated... He
separated out an ox. He said an עולה, olah, he didn't say
which type of קרבן korban he would bring. He could have brought
a little sheep, but he was going to be Mr. generous and
he separated out an ox. בא אחר וגנב ba acher v'ganav and
somebody came and stole the ox and burgled it. מי פטר גנב
נפשיה בכבש? mi patar ganav nafshaih b'keves? Can the גנב ganav give
back to the guy and say, okay, I stole something, I made
you lose out because you have to bring an עולה, olah, but
you know what? To bring the עולה olah you're obligated in, you're
not going to have to bring an ox. You could fulfill your
obligation by just bringing a lamb.
Wait a minute, meaning he has to pay the קרן keren of
the of what he stole but the כפל kefel part would be...
No, this is even about the קרן, keren, right? It's to begin,
you know, it's that you're not חייב chayav for stealing קדשים? kodshim?
I mean רש"י, Rashi, you're right, what you say is a good
point, and the גמרא Gemara never, to my recollection, never explicitly addressed
the question of קרן keren by גנב קדשים ganav kodshim or whatever;
it was mostly focusing on כפל, kefel, but presumably it's the same
point. Like if let's say it was not חייב באחריותה. chayav b'achrayutah.
Let's say you said הרי עלי עולה, harei alai olah, right? And
I stole... and not like הרי זו עולה, harei zo olah, and
I stole your עולה. olah. I wouldn't have to pay you anything,
right? I just stole a קרבן korban which you don't suffer as
a loss of. Okay? So there's no חיוב. chiyuv. So according to
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, when you're קדשים שחייב באחריותן, kodshim she'chayav b'achrayutan,
then the רבי שמעון'ס חידוש Rabbi Shimon's chidush is, right? So a
normal קדשים kodshim that you're not חייב באחריותה, chayav b'achrayutah, I don't
pay you anything. Now, if you took a נדר, neder, if you
weren't רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, you might say why would I have
to pay you if I stole it, גרמי, garmi, like I indirectly
caused you a loss? But it wouldn't be a real תורה חיוב
Torah chiyuv of גניבה, gneivah, because at the end of the day
it really isn't yours. רבי שמעון'ס חידוש Rabbi Shimon's chidush is a
type of a דבר הגורם לממון כממון דמי. davar ha'goreim l'mamon k'mamon
dami. It's not just indirect damages, it's treated as if it really
is yours. But that's relevant not just for the כפל, kefel, it's
relevant even for the קרן, keren, even for the principle. So what
רבא'ס Rava's question is is, how much is it your animal? Right?
Is it your animal only to the degree of its replacement value?
Right? What is the replacement value of this animal? So רבא'ס Rava's
question is, you might want to replace it with an ox, but
you're only obligated to replace it with a sheep. So when I
steal it from you, we're talking just about paying the principle, how
much do you... is it your animal that you lost? Right? What
is the replacement value of it? So that's what his question is.
הרי עלי עולה והפריש שור בא אחר וגנבו. harei alai olah v'hifrish
shor ba acher v'ganavo. מי פטר גנב
נפשיה בכבש לרבנן? mi patar ganav nafshaih b'keves l'Rabbanan? For a lamb
according to the רבנן. Rabbanan. בעולת העוף לרבי אלעזר בן עזריה? b'olat
ha'of l'Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah? For an עולת העוף olat ha'of for
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה. Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah. What's the debate? דתנן,
d'tnan, we taught in the משנה. Mishna. הרי עלי עולה. harei alai
olah. Somebody took a vow. What is the default that we should
assume this person is obligated in?
יביא כבש. yavi keves. The רבנן Rabbanan say he should bring a
lamb. Certainly you'd fulfill your obligation if you brought an ox, presumably
you would also fulfill it if you brought a bird. But what
should we assume you mean? What is like the minimum, you know,
the general minimum interpretation of that? רבי אלעזר בן עזריה אומר יביא
תור או בן יונה. Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah omer yavi tor o
ben yonah. No, he could bring some type of a turtle dove.
Okay. So, you can fulfill your obligation by bringing something less. Do
I have to pay you for the full value because right now,
you know, it is your ox that you sanctified?
On the other hand, the reason it's considered yours is because you'll
have to replace it. But you don't have to replace it with
an ox. So מי אמרינן, mi amrinan, do we say שם עולה
קביל עילויה? sheim olah kabil ileih? One minute. Do we say that,
look, you accepted an עולה olah and therefore I'm replacing... I'm giving
you something that you can use as your עולה? olah? או דילמא,
o dilma, or do we say מצי אמר ליה, matzi amar leih,
no, אנא מצוה מובחרת בעינא למיעבד. ana mitzvah muvcheret beina l'meavad. I
want to do a better מצוה. mitzvah. You know, so it's clear
from my actions that I want to bring a big one and
that in practice I will replace it with another ox because I've
demonstrated that. So even though I'm not technically obligated to, that's ultimately
what you made me lose. So the גמרא Gemara says בתר דאיבעיא
הדר פשטה. batar d'ibeiya hadar pashitah. After he raised the question, he
concluded. גנב פטר עצמו בכבש לרבנן בעולת העוף לרבי אלעזר בן עזריה.
ganav patar atzmo b'keves l'Rabbanan b'olat ha'of l'Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah. Yes,
you can exempt himself by returning something of that value. Now that's
an interesting question. Does he need only literally if you return an
animal? Or does he mean just return the value of a כבש?
keves? The value... presumably the value would suffice as well, assuming the
animal itself is dead and is not around. And it makes sense,
because that's the only legal obligation that the owner has to replace
it with. So it's נבך nebach that the owner lost it, but
there's a lot of נבך'ס nebachs going around. If I said הרי
זו עולה, harei zo olah, not הרי עלי, harei alai, with an
ox, you wouldn't have to give me anything. Okay. So the only
real legally obligated replacement value is that amount.
I was just going to ask... what? At what if I just
said זו?
zo? Then even according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon you wouldn't have...
let's finish to the משנה Mishna and then I'll take the question.
מר Mar says like this: רב אחא בריה דרב איקא מתני לה
בהדיא. Rav Acha breih d'Rav Ika matni lah b'hedya. He taught that
this wasn't even a question, this was a straight teaching of רבא.
Rava. אמר רבא הרי עלי עולה והפריש שור ובא אחר וגנבו פטר
עצמו בכבש לרבנן ובעולת העוף לרבי אלעזר בן עזריה.
amar Rava harei alai
olah v'hifrish shor u'ba acher u'gnavo patar atzmo b'keves l'Rabbanan u'v'olat ha'of
l'Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah.
That רבא Rava didn't even have a question, this was just clearly
his straight teaching. This is the only legally mandated replacement value, so
that's the only thing that you have to pay. Yes?
I was just thinking about the case where if you ask someone
to take
תרומה, terumah, right? You know, and then usually there's the בינונים beinonim
and then whatever. Don't we say you go like what he does
normally?
Yeah, but that's a question about what's the implicit שליחות... shlichut... Here
the reason is to say that is that it's a question about
not what you will do. If you said הרי זו harei zo
and I knew that you're the type of guy that if you
lost it you're going to replace it, doesn't mean that I have
to pay you if I steal it, right? That's just a decision
you make. That's not its actual legal value or its the- or
the legal consequence of its loss to
you. Okay, next משנה. mishna. Okay, this משנה mishna finally wraps up
like a series of משניות. mishnayot. Remember these משניות mishnayot started, you
know, you sell something, you steal and then you're מקדיש makdish it,
you're מקדיש makdish and then you slaughter it, or you slaughter it
and then you're מקדיש makdish it, you steal from the father, father
dies, all these scenarios, right? And the משניות mishnayot have been playing
out with these variations. And what are the witnesses saying, and the
witnesses say this, and then the witnesses say that. Okay, so this
is sort of the last of those series. So let's take a
look. מכרה חוץ מאחד ממאה שבו. makhra hutz mi-echad mimeo shebo. Let's
say you sold it with the exclusion of one of a hundred.
Like I'm going to sell it, I stole Michael's sheep here, Charlie,
and I'll sell it to you, but I retain ownership over the
right foot. Okay, the right front foot. Okay, so I didn't sell
you the whole thing. Okay, או שהייתה בו שותפות. o she-hayetah bo
shutafut.
Or Michael and I owned the sheep in שותפות shutafut and I
sold his- and I sold his half away, like I just stole
it and I sold it to Charlie there under Michael's nose. Okay,
but half of it was already mine. Okay, or all these cases
you're going to be exempt. Okay, the שותפות shutafut you might remember
similar to the case of the guy who steals from his father
and then his father dies and then he sells it, so that
by the time of the sale he was already a part owner.
So since by the time of the sale he wasn't selling something
that was 100% somebody else's, it was a little bit his when
he sold it, remember that scenario? He stole it, the father died,
so then it became a little bit his. So since at the
time of the sale it was a little bit his, he is
not חייב hayav for the sale. So certainly here where presumably even
at the time of stealing it was a little bit his, so
when he's selling something, he's selling something that is not all somebody
else's, it's also something that's a little bit his, he's not חייב
hayav for the sale. Okay, for paying four and
five. השוחט ונתנבלה בידו. ha-shohet venitnevlah beyado.
He shechted it and it became a נבלה neveilah as he was
shechting. He did a bad job of שחיטה. shechitah. So even if
you say שחיטה שאינה ראויה שמה שחיטה, shechitah she-einah re'uyah shemah shechitah,
that if you do the act physically correctly, even if for a
halakhic reason the meat isn't kosher, because let's say the animal was
טריפה, treifah, right? That's the debate of Rabbi Shimon and the חכמים,
Hakhamim, whether that counts as a שחיטה shechitah or not. Everybody agrees
if it's not a physically correct act of שחיטה, shechitah, if you
shechted it and you moved the knife in a way so that
it wasn't even considered to be an act of שחיטה, shechitah, it's
not some external reason that's preventing the meat from being מותר. muttar.
The point is you didn't do a שחיטה shechitah on it. Okay,
then everybody agrees you're exempt. Okay, or הנוחר, ha-noher, if you basically
just like, like, you know, and
it says וטבחו, u-tevaho, right? Why can't וטבחו u-tevaho mean like I
chopped it up? Yeah, so וטבחו u-tevaho is used, right, וטבחו u-tevaho
is used, וטבוח טבח
והכן,
u-tavoah
tevach
vehachen, וטבחו u-tevaho is used specifically in context of a sense of
slaughtering to prepare meat. That's like the context of the word
טבח. taveah. Okay, so the גמרא gemara understands that וטבחו u-tevaho is
the- is the same as שחיטה. shechitah. Okay, but you're right. I
mean, the גמרא- gemara and there is a גמרא gemara that questions
שחיטה שאינה ראויה shechitah she-einah re'uyah that וטבחו u-tevaho actually, according to
some, the actual basis of שחיטה שאינה ראויה לא שמה שחיטה shechitah
she-einah re'uyah lo shemah shechitah was וטבוח טבח והכן u-tavoah tevach vehachen
is a word from טביחה, tevachah, not from שחיטה. shechitah. Actually, it
was Yosef who was taking the role, right? Well, I understand. I
understand. Wherever you normally- I understand. I understand. Okay, but anyway, but
וטבחו u-tevaho means to prepare meat. Okay. השוחט ונתנבלה בידו, ha-shohet venitnevlah
beyado, הנוחר ha-noher והמעקר. veha-me'aker. הנוחר noher is like a way of
killing it without even doing שחיטה shechitah at all, or המעקר me'aker
is like you're- you're tearing out the- the trachea and the esophagus.
In all those cases, you didn't do an act of שחיטה. shechitah.
משלם תשלומי כפל ואינו משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. meshalem tashlumei khefel ve-eino
meshalem tashlumei arba'ah ve-hamishah. You don't pay four and five. So the
stuff at the end
is
pretty obvious,
just don't think that even though the Rabbis say שחיטה שאינה ראויה
שמה שחיטה, shechitah she-einah re'uyah shemah shechitah, that's only when there's an
external halakhic problem. If it's not a שחיטה shechitah at all, clearly
it's not a שחיטה. shechitah. But the first cases of מכירה mekhirah
are more interesting, and those are the ones the גמרא gemara is
going to deal with. So let's take a look at the גמרא.
gemara. מאי חוץ מאחד ממאה שבו? mai hutz mi-echad mimeo shebo? When
it says if you sell it 99%, you retain 1%, it's not
a מכירה. mekhirah. Does it literally mean any 1%, which 1%? Says
the גמרא. gemara. Okay, so אמר רב, amar Rav, חוץ מדבר הניתר
עמו בשחיטה. hutz midavar hanittar imo bishchitah. You have to leave over
some type- some of the meat, something that the שחיטה shechitah relates
to. If I left over, we'll see in a minute, the wool,
a horn, a tooth, a- you know, something of that nature, then
it is not leaving something over. The act of שחיטה shechitah only
applies to the thing that requires שחיטה, shechitah, to the meat of
the animal. Okay, so you have to leave over, retain for yourself,
something that becomes permissible through the שחיטה, shechitah, some bit of meat.
If I retain the wool, you say that I retained a significant
part of it?
I understand, but- but the- we're asking for the חיוב hiyuv of
the act of שחיטה. shechitah. Oh, no, sorry, excuse me, I missed
the point. We're not talking about שחיטה, shechitah, we're talking about מכירה.
mekhirah. But what this is assuming, and you might remember there was
a debate of Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש: Resh Lakish: does something
have to be חייב hayav for one to be חייב hayav for
the other? So here though we're assuming though that the parameters of
what does it mean to sell all of it would be the
same parameters of what's considered the all of it when it comes
to שחיטה. shechita. So that's important. We're not dealing with שחיטה, shechita,
we're dealing with מכירה. mechira. But how much does it mean, and
everybody agrees מכירה mechira means you got to sell the whole thing?
But the whole thing as defined through the lens of שחיטה. shechita.
And Michael's right, if you ignore שחיטה, shechita, wool is a significant
thing to be retaining for yourself. But if you're seeing it through
the lens of שחיטה, shechita, the שחיטה's shechita's only relevant to the
meat, so the מכירה mechira is only measured by the meat. That's
what רב Rav says. חוץ מדבר הניתר עמו בשחיטה. Chutz midavar hanitar
imo bishchita. But לוי Levi אמר, amar, חוץ מגיזותיה, chutz migizoteha, no,
like Michael said, anything you leave over for yourself, you don't define
it through the lens of שחיטה. shechita. If you just leave over
the wool, that's leaving something over. Okay.
But and not the horn though?
Ah, maybe even the horn actually, we'll see in a minute that
the horn might be even more of a leaving over because the
horn remains naturally attached. וכן תניא במתניסא, Vechen tanya bematnisa, so we
taught in a ברייתא braita similar to לוי, Levi, חוץ מגיזותיה, chutz
migizoteha, that just leaving over the shearings is considered a leaving something
over, a holding back. מיתיבי, Meitivei, I'll ask you on רב. Rav.
We have a three-way debate in a ברייתא. braita. מכר חוץ מידה,
חוץ מרגלה, machar chutz miyadah chutz miraglah, you sold it with the
exception of the hand or the foot, או חוץ מקרנה o chutz
mikarnah or the horn, so a horn is not ניתר בשחיטה, nitar
bishchita, right? או חוץ מגיזותיה o chutz migizoteha with the exception of
the shearings, אינו משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה, eino meshalem tashlumei arba'a vachamisha,
you don't pay four and five. So that's לוי. Levi. Anything you
leave over, even something that is naturally shorn away, that is not
meat, that is not edible, a horn, shearings, that's you're exempt. That's
לוי. Levi. רבי אומר, Rebbe omer, רבי Rebbe says, דבר המעכב בשחיטה
אינו משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה Davar hame'akev bishchita eino meshalem tashlumei arba'a
vachamisha ושאינו מעכב בשחיטה משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. veshe'eino me'akev bishchita meshalem
tashlumei arba'a vachamisha. He says like רב, Rav, but he goes רב
Rav one narrower. He says no, no, you're only חייב chayav for
selling something relevant that's relevant to the שחיטה. shechita. But it's not
even meat. It's only the things that would prevent the שחיטה shechita
from being כשר kosher if it was not around if it was
taken away from the animal. So if you say I'm holding back
the heart, I'm holding back the brain, or I'm holding back, you
know, a side bone that if the animal was missing this thighbone
it would be a טריפה, treifa, that's considered to be holding something
back. But to be holding back a little piece of meat that
even if it were missing, the animal would still be able to
be שחט, shacht, it would still be a כשר kosher animal, that's
not holding it back. Okay, so this is רב Rav but רב
Rav squared. That's okay, but he's basically saying, you're only חייב chayav
for מכירה mechira on something that's part of the act of שחיטה,
shechita, but part of the act of שחיטה shechita is defined as
not something that the שחיטה shechita makes permissible, but something that's required
for the שחיטה shechita to be a good שחיטה. shechita. That's what
רבי Rebbe says.
It has to be there in terms of
it has to be at if this thing were missing from the
animal, the שחיטה shechita would not be a good שחיטה. shechita.
Okay, as opposed to the
horn, but or even as opposed to the foot. Okay, an animal
could be missing a foot and not be a טריפה. treifa. רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר אומר, Rebbe Shimon ben Elazar omer, חוץ מקרנה, chutz
mikarnah, אינו משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. eino meshalem tashlumei arba'a vachamisha. No,
that if you leave off the horn, you don't pay, because the
horn is a something that stays attached to the animal, so we
don't measure it by שחיטה, shechita, we measure it just by מכירה.
mechira. But what does it mean to sell the full thing? Well,
things that naturally remain always part of the animal, like the horn.
חוץ מגיזותיה, Chutz migizoteha, to sell it without its shearings, משלם תשלומי
ארבעה וחמישה, meshalem tashlumei arba'a vachamisha, you would pay it because sometimes
animals are shorn. So you can imagine an animal with its wool
and without its wool. So it's still considered the whole animal. But
missing something that is normally not removed, that's a non-whole animal. So
you have two approaches that ignore שחיטה, shechita, and they just say
whole. So, you know, whole means missing anything is not whole, or
missing something that's not normally taken away is not whole. Okay, and
you have another approach that focuses on שחיטה, shechita, but on what's
necessary for שחיטה. shechita. So the גמרא Gemara works it through. בשלמא
Bishlama לוי, Levi, it works according to לוי Levi כתנא קמא. ketanna
kamma. He holds like the תנא קמא tanna kamma that says if
it's missing anything, even the shearings, you're not חייב. chayav. אלא רב
כמאן? Ela Rav keman? Who's רב Rav going like? The one he's
closest like is רבי, Rebbe, but רבי's Rebbe's even more narrow than
רב. Rav. So כמאן אמר, keman amar, who's he going like? So
the גמרא Gemara says no, רב דאמר כי האי תנא. Rav de'amar
ki hai tanna. רב Rav says like the following תנא. tanna. We
got a fourth opinion. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braita,
another version of רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Rebbe Shimon ben Elazar. Okay,
in our ברייתא braita he said it made a difference between the
horn and the shearings, but here's what he says in this ברייתא.
braita. דתניא רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר, Detanya Rebbe Shimon ben Elazar
omer, מכר חוץ מידה Machar chutz miyadah, חוץ מרגלה, chutz miraglah, אינו
משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. eino meshalem tashlumei arba'a vachamisha. If you leave
over a foot or a leg, you don't pay, because that's meat,
and meat is connected to שחיטה. shechita. This is רב's Rav's idea,
so anything that the שחיטה shechita affects is something that you can't
leave over. אבל חוץ מקרנה חוץ מגיזותיה, Aval chutz mikarnah chutz migizoteha,
but if you leave over a horn or the shearings, which are
not related to the שחיטה, shechita, משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה, meshalem tashlumei
arba'a vachamisha, you pay it. Okay, we're great, we have four opinions.
לוי Levi matches up with one, רב Rav matches up with one,
and two other approaches. Now, what are these debates what's the debate
about? במאי קמיפלגי? Bemai kamiflagi? What's the debate about? תנא
קמא סבר וטבחו כולו בעינן. Tanna kamma savar utvacho kulo beinan. The
תנא קמא's tanna kamma's of the opinion, slaughter it means the whole
thing. wherever they leave the whole
ומכרו u'macharo כולה בעינן kula ba'inan and selling it means sell the
whole thing, you know, as simple as it said. Anything that's missing
from the מכירה mechira is missing. Now I assume by the טביחה,
tavicha, if you were to cut off a horn and cut off
the... the wool and then שחט shacht it... like, I don't know,
my guess would be that you would still be חייב. chayav. That
that still is that... it might be that טביחה, tavicha, it's the
whole thing as relates to שחיטה, shechita, as relates to what the
שחיטה's shechita relevant for. That might be measured by the meat. But
at least by the מכירה, mechira, that's measured on its own terms,
not in... not through the lens of שחיטה. shechita. So מכירה mechira
measured on its own terms is if anything is missing, it's not
a מכירה. mechira. Although who knows, maybe you would say the same
by שחיטה shechita as well, even if you cut off the horn
or cut off the... the wool before you שחט shacht it.
Even if I set everything to ownership but one hair?
Apparently. Okay, if you're a... if you're a smart גנב, ganav, you
know what to do. Yep. Okay, so it has to be the
whole thing. So רבי סבר, Rebbe savar, Rebbe holds, וטבחו מידי דהוה
בטביחה, u'tevacho midi d'hava b'tavicha, something that's relevant to the טביחה, tavicha,
לאפוקי מידי דלא הוה בטביחה, l'afokei midi d'lo hava b'tavicha, to exclude
something that is... that is not necessary for the שחיטה. shechita. So
anything that you don't need to be part of the animal to
make the שחיטה כשר shechita kosher is not your... you know, you
could... you could sell without that thing, without a foot, since the
animal would still be able to be שחט shachted without a foot,
you could sell that and that's not considered a non-full sale. ומכרו
דומיא דטביחה. u'macharo dumya d'tavicha. So the same way if you cut
off a foot and you שחט shachted it, you'd be חייב chayav
because the foot doesn't prevent the שחיטה shechita from working. If you
hold back a foot when you sell it, you're also חייב. chayav.
ומכרו דומיא דטביחה. u'macharo dumya d'tavicha. This makes it sound by the
way that according to the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, if I just
cut off a hair before I even שחט shachted it, that it
literally means the whole thing, whether שחיטה, shechita, whether מכירה. mechira. So
like, right, like Michael said, not even שיור, shiyur, all the shearings,
just cut off one hair. Okay, so it's a funny idea. Okay,
but the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says literally everything. רבי Rebbe says
no, no, no, only stuff necessary for the שחיטה, shechita, and therefore
the same way that's true by the שחיטה, shechita, that if you
cut off a foot you'd still be חייב chayav because... because you
can still do a שחיטה shechita without a foot, so if you
sell it without a foot you're also חייב. chayav. But something that
makes it not able to be שחט, shachted, you'd be פטור. patur.
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר סבר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar savar, Rabbi Shimon
ben Elazar is of the opinion, קרנא דלא למיגזז קיימא הוה שיור,
karna d'lo l'migzaz kayma hava shiyur, a horn that normally is not
shorn off, that is leaving something else. It doesn't have to be
similar to שחט, shechting, it's defined the whole thing just on its
own terms, but a whole thing means things that are always attached
to it. So anything you cut off from it or you don't
sell from it that is normally attached, you're exempt.
But... where were we? קרנא דלא למיגזז קיימא הוה שיור, karna d'lo
l'migzaz kayma hava shiyur, and he doesn't pay תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. tashlumei
arba'ah v'chamishah. גיזותיה, gizoteha, but the shearings, דלמיגזז קיימי, d'l'migzas kaymi, are
normally shorn off, that's not considered part of the whole thing. So
in that case, לא הוה שיור, lo hava shiyur, you're not leaving
something off by not selling the shearings, ומשלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה, u'meshalem
tashlumei arba'ah v'chamishah, he pay for and five.
ואידך תנא דבי רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, v'idach tana d'bei Rabbi Shimon
ben Elazar, the other ברייתא Braita that has a different version of
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, which is the position of... of רב, Rav,
that something that is meat is considered holding back, סבר, savar, ידה
ורגלה דצרכי טביחה הוה שיור. yada v'ragla d'tzarchei tavicha hava shiyur. A
foot and a leg that are needed... not that the שחיטה shechita
needs them, but they need the טביחה, tavicha, that they only become
permissible with the שחיטה. shechita. So... so that's leaving something over. By
שחט shechting it is only the whole of the thing defined through
the lens of שחט shechting is things that the שחט shechting makes
permissible. So if you cut those off before שחיטה, shechita, you'd be
exempt, and if you sold it without those things, you'd also be
exempt. ולא... okay, ידה ורגלה דצרכי טביחה tavicha, הוה שיור, ולא הוה
משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. v'lo hava meshalem tashlumei arba'ah v'chamishah. קרנה וגיזותיה,
karna v'gizoteha, its horns and its shearings, דלא צרכו טביחה, d'lo tzarchu
tavicha, that don't need the טביחה, לא הוה שיור, lo hava shiyur,
are not considered holding it back. Okay, very nice. Four... two versions
that see it through the lens of שחיטה, shechita, either that the
שחיטה shechita needs it or it needs the שחיטה. shechita. Two versions
that see it through the... not the lens of שחיטה, shechita, just
define it as whole, and whole completely, literally whole, or whole in
the sense of at least things that are always attached to it.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says, קשיא רבי שמעון בן אלעזר ארבי
שמעון בן אלעזר, kashya Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar a'Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar,
we have two versions of Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, he's contradicting himself.
Fine, תרי תנאי אליבא דרבי שמעון בן אלעזר, trei tanna'i aliba d'Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar, which is clearly the case here. There are two
versions of Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, two different debates of what Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar held. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our Rabbis taught: הגונב
הקיטוע, ha'gonev haktua, let's say this definition of whole is only relative
to the way it was stolen. Let's say you stole an animal
that already had a leg cut off, את החיגרת, et hachigeret, or
an animal that was lame, which is obviously less of a חידוש
chiddush because there it is physically whole. את הסומא, et hasuma, or
blind, also less of a חידוש chiddush than an animal that literally
doesn't have a leg. Anyway, וכן הגונב בהמת השותפים חייב, v'chen hagonev
behemas hashutfim chayav, or if you steal a בהמה behema that's of
partners, you're חייב. chayav. והשותפים שגנבו פטורין. v'hashutfim sheganvu paturin. The partners
themselves in partnership stole, then they are פטורין. paturin. So now we're
going to look at that second part in a minute, but before
we get to that, let's first describe the first part. So first...
go back to your friend... Exactly. Right. So the first part is
like I said that hole is relative to the way it was
stolen. If it was stolen and it was missing a limb you'd
still be חייב. chayav. If you went ahead and sold it or
שחט shechted it or whatever, not if it was a טרפה. treifah.
Okay. If you steal from your partner you're exempt because then you're
part owner so you're not stealing something that's totally not yours. Okay,
I'm sorry, where were we? גונב בהמת gonev behemas oh sorry, if
you stole from partners, excuse me, I steal something that was owned
by David and Michael combined. Okay, so of course I'm חייב, chayav,
right, it's fully not mine. Just because it's owned by partners I'm
going to be חייב. chayav. That's גונב בהמת השותפים. gonev behemas hashutfim.
Now what שותפים שגנבו פטור, shutfim sheganvu patur, that's going to be
interesting. What does it mean partners who stole? So that's the one
we're going to explore now. Partners in crime. But why are you
exempt? And not only that, ותניא, v'tanya, we have a ברייתא braita
that teaches שותפים שגנבו חייבים shutfim sheganvu chayavim that partners who steal
are חייבים. chayavim. So what's going on here? So אמר רב נחמן
amar Rav Nachman לא קשיא. lo kashya. There's two types of cases
of partners who steal, who burgle. לא קשיא. lo kashya. כאן בשותף
שגנב מחברו, kan b'shataf sheganav michavero, כאן בשותף שגנב מעלמא. kan b'shataf
sheganav mealma. When it says partners who steal it's really a poor
way of saying it. It means Michael and I are partners in
this sheep and I steal the sheep away from Michael. So then
we know
why I'm exempt. I mean I'm exempt from four and five, right,
not from כפל, kefel, but because four and five you need to
sell or שחט shecht all of it,
sell all of it, meaning it's all not mine. So in this
case if I steal a sheep that's half mine and I take
away and run away with the whole sheep, I'm חייב chayav in
כפל kefel to Michael for his half but I'm not חייב chayav
for שחיטה ומכירה shechita u-mechira because I'm selling something that's or שחט
shechting something that's part mine. So that's שותפים. shutfim. It doesn't sound
like שותפים שגנבו shutfim sheganvu means that. It sounds like we stole
it combined. But we're reading it as one partner stole from his
other. Then you're exempt from four and five. That's the case when
you're exempt.
כאן בשותף שגנב מחברו. kan b'shataf sheganav michavero. One minute. כאן בשותף
שגנב מעלמא. kan b'shataf sheganav mealma. When are you חייב? chayav? That's
when you're פטור. patur. When are you חייב? chayav? If you're a
partner and you steal from somebody else's. Now what does it mean?
Are you stealing it with your friend? That's the partners in crime.
Okay, so if you're two people and we'll unpack that in a
minute. But let's say Michael and I sneak into somebody's yard and
we steal the sheep combined. Now you could say did we do
a מעשה קניין maaseh kinyan on it? Did we both do a
מעשה קניין? maaseh kinyan? But let's say somehow we define it as
we both did a מעשה קניין. maaseh kinyan. Okay, so we both
are גנבים. ganavim. So now we both together owe the owner. And
even though each of us might only wind up paying half but
we both did an act of גניבה. geneivah. Now the interesting question
is the חידוש chiddush here is going to be who did the
שחיטה, shechita, who did the מכירה? mechira? You might remember there were
questions about שליח לדבר עבירה shliach l'dvar aveirah by the שחיטה shechita
and the מכירה. mechira.
Yeah, I was going to ask. Let's say I'm manning the lookout
car but you actually go in.
Right, so yeah, no no no. That's a good point. So שותפים
שגנבו shutfim sheganvu only means right, it's not like those crime movies
or whatever. שותפים שגנבו shutfim sheganvu only means that we both literally
lifted up the sheep together. And even there you have to figure
out like so is that considered a מעשה קניין? maaseh kinyan? I
mean if just סתם stam Michael and I want to buy a
sheep from David. Can we both pick it up together? Right, would
that consider because if each one of us didn't, you know, is
that a מעשה קניין? maaseh kinyan? Anyway, but that is the scenario.
Okay.
So my point is if I'm manning the lookout then I'm not
חייב chayav in anything then? Exactly. Okay, but I thought the getaway
car doesn't get the same amount of...
Yeah,
but here he gets nothing. It doesn't matter the getaway car. You
might your guy could be doing everything except picking up the sheep.
Right? He could be binding or you know gagging and binding the
owner while I take all the sheep out and I'm the only
גנב ganav in the case. Okay anyway, so if I steal from
my partner then I pay כפל kefel but I don't pay four
and five because I'm not שוחט shechting or selling all of it
that's not mine. Part of it is mine, it's not completely not
mine. But if partners steal they are חייב. chayav. Okay. כאן בשותף
שגנב מחברו, kan b'shataf sheganav michavero, כאן בשותף שגנב מעלמא. kan b'shataf
sheganav mealma. אתא רבא לרב נחמן. asei Rava l'Rav Nachman. Rava asked
Rav Nachman this distinction. We have another ברייתא. braita.
יכול שותף שגנב מחברו yachol shataf sheganav michavero if a partner stole
from his
partner או שותפים שגנבו o shutfim sheganvu or partners together stole יהיו
חייבים yehuyu chayavim maybe they'd have to pay four and five. תלמוד
לומר וטבחו כולו בעינן וליכא. talmud lomar u-tvacho kulo ba'inan v'leika. You're
not slaughtering all of it. So you see that even when partners
are partners in crime they do not pay. אלא אמר רב נחמן
ela amar Rav Nachman so now we're going to distinguish between two
types of partners in crime. לא קשיא. lo kashya. כאן בשותף שגנב
וטבח לדעת חברו, kan b'shataf sheganav v'tavach l'daas chaveiro, כאן בשותף שגנב
וטבח שלא לדעת חברו. kan b'shataf sheganav v'tavach shelo l'daas chaveiro. This
is going to get to the question of who has to do
the slaughtering or the selling. Michael and I combined steal David's sheep.
Okay. If Michael then שחט shechts it because and we say Michael
now שחט shecht the sheep and then we'll you know eat the
meat and it's done with our mutual understanding then we're חייב chayav
four and five. If however Michael goes ahead and שחט shechts it
without me knowing I thought we were going to raise it. It
was going to be my little lamb that I was going to
bring to school. Okay but Michael went ahead and he שחט shechted
it. In that case we're not חייב chayav four and five. Why?
Michael's also a גנב. ganav. He שחט shechted it, but he only
שחט shecht his half as it were. Okay and he didn't שחט
shecht my half with my permission and therefore ironically he שחט shechted
something that was fully not his. It was a hundred percent David's,
okay, but he was only a half גנב ganav over it. I
was the other half גנב. ganav. And therefore his שחיטה shchita is
not מחייב mechayev him because it's not the שחיטה shchita of the
two of us combined. Only if it's done with my understanding. Okay?
So בשותפות דבר שלא לדעת חברו. b'shutfos davar shelo l'daas chaveiro. And
we're going to unpack that in a minute but first we're going
to go deal with another point. בעי רבי ירמיה, Ba'ei Rabi Yirmiya,
רבי ירמיה Rabi Yirmiya asked the following question.
מכר חוץ משלושים יום. Machar chutz mishloshim yom. Let's say you sold
it not leaving over a piece of the animal, but leaving over
a piece of ownership. Okay,
I don't think we have this case. I stole it from Charlie
there and I sold it to Michael, but I said Michael, I'm
selling it to you, but after that you'll own it after 30
days. I get to use it for the first 30 days. Or
maybe, yeah. חוץ משלושים יום Chutz mishloshim yom is a funny question
because you would think it would be פשוט pashut that after 30
days came, it would be like waiting 30 days and then selling
it, right? So, you know, why but but maybe I was brought
to court before the 30 days had even arrived or something. I
don't know. That's a weird idea. חוץ מ... Chutz m... the other
cases are a little more obvious why you should be
פטור. pater. חוץ מעבודה... Chutz m'avoda... I'm sorry, did I skip?
חוץ ממלאכתה. Chutz mimlachtah. Michael, you own it if you want to
שחט shecht it, but as long as you're not interested in שחיטה
shechting it, I get to use it. So that's a clear point.
I didn't fully sell it to Michael. Okay. חוץ מעוברה. Chutz me'ubarah.
I'm selling it to you but I keep the fetus, okay, if
it's pregnant. מהו? Mahu? Is that considered to sell it fully?
אליבא דמאן דאמר עובר ירך אמו הוא, Aliba d'man d'amar ubar yerech
imo hu, if you say the fetus is like a limb of
the mother, לא תיבעי לך דשייר בה. lo tibai lach d'shayar bah.
Of course you left something over, you left over a limb, okay,
and it certainly is דבר הניתר בשחיטה. davar hanitar b'shchita. Right. כי
תיבעי לך אליבא דמאן דאמר עובר לאו ירך אמו הוא. Ki tibai
lach aliba d'man d'amar ubar lav yerech imo hu. That last question
of the עובר ubar would be a question even if you say
that עובר ubar is not a part of the mother. You can't
say עובר ubar these days without thinking about your car service. Okay,
מאי? mai? What's the story? מימר אמרינן כיון דמחובר בה הוי שיור,
Memar amrinan keivan d'mechubar bah havei shiyur, do we say, look, since
it's attached to it, even though it's not considered a part of
the sheep, but it is physically attached to the sheep, that is
leaving something off. או דילמא, O dilma, or do we say, כיון
דלמיפרש מינה קאי, keivan d'lemifrash minei kai, no, but it's maybe it's
sort of like I don't know the shearings. It's something that's going
to be removed from it and it'll even be more naturally removed
than the shearings. So maybe it's not considered. Maybe the shearings would
be leaving something over, but retaining the עובר ubar is not leaving
something over.
לעתיד לפרושה, L'atid lipursha, what about that?
That's an interesting question. לא הוי שיור. Lo havei shiyur. So איכא
דאמרי, ikka d'amri, so that's the question. So we don't know about
the earlier one of חוץ ממלאכתה, chutz mimlachtah, but חוץ מעוברה chutz
me'ubarah we're focusing in on that. That's more similar to the things
we discussed earlier. How much is that considered a fully part of
the sheep or not? איכא דאמרי, Ikka d'amri, some say, כיון דלאו
ירך אמו הוא, keivan d'lav yerech imo hu, since it's not halachically
considered part of the mother, לא הוי שיור. lo havei shiyur. Do
we say that? או דילמא, O dilma, or do we say, כיון
דצריך לאישוריה בהדה, keivan d'tzarich l'ishorei bahada, it's needed to continue to
grow in the mother's womb. It's not just that it is technically
connected, but it even needs the mother to continue to grow. I'm
sorry. No, I made that up. לאישוריה בהדה בשחיטה. L'ishorei bahada b'shchita.
I'm sorry. It needs to be in the mother so that the
שחיטה shchita would make it מותר. muttar. The שחיטה shchita will מתיר
mattir it. Even though it's not part of the mother, right, if
you שחט shecht a mother cow and you find a calf in
it, you can eat the calf and the calf gets up and
walks around, right, that's the case of בן פקועה. ben pekua. I
heard that somebody, did you hear this thing recently, like 30 years
ago in ישיבה Yeshiva we used to joke about this, but now
somebody's actually starting it, a בן פקועה ben pekua farm. You raise
animals that are that are you intentionally שחט shecht animals when they're
about to give birth, they give birth to animals, those animals don't
require שחיטה, shchita, and then they have their own baby animals and
then you can just have all these animals that never require שחיטה.
shchita. So somebody, I mean when I learned this 30 years ago
in ישיבה Yeshiva we made this joke, oh I could start a
בן פקועה ben pekua farm, and actually somebody's actually trying to do
it. So anyway, okay, but whatever.
Can you combine that with like milk that was within the
mother,
right, so it's not really מילכיג, milchig, right. Exactly. או דילמא כיון
דצריך לאישוריה בהדה בשחיטה, O dilma keivan d'tzarich l'ishorei bahada b'shchita, or
do we say that even though halachically it's not a unit with
the mother, it needs to be in the mother so that the
שחיטה shchita will be relevant for it, so therefore it really is
like ניתר אמו בשחיטה, nitir immo b'shchita, right, כמאן דשייר בגופה דמי,
keman d'shayar begufa dami, that is like you left a piece of
the body over. תיקו, Teku, we don't know. So we don't know
the עובר ubar case, and the גמרא Gemara doesn't even try to
unpack the other cases about like, you know, retaining it חוץ מ...
chutz m... you know, חוץ ממלאכתה chutz mimlachtah and so on. Okay,
now let's take another look, and this other question that we're going
to get to is going to circle back to the question about
partners. בעי רב פפא, Ba'ei Rav Pappa, רב פפא Rav Pappa asked,
גנבה קיטעה ומכרה מהו? ganava kita umachrah mahu? You stole it, you
cut off a limb and then you sold it. Okay, so מי
אמרינן מאי דגנב לא זבין, mi amrinan mai d'ganav lo zavin, what
you stole you didn't sell, you didn't sell the whole thing. Okay,
so the same way if I had said I am keeping the
ownership of the limb I'd be exempt. When you cut off the
limb you're also exempt, או דילמא, o dilma, or do we say
מאי דזבין הלא שייר? mai dzavin halo shier? What you sold, you
sold fully. You sold the full, you know, the full animal that
you actually, that was
taken, sure a little bit of it.
Exactly, I assure some of it and then I sold it. Absolutely.
So when we said like we have two cases: you retained the
limb, you're exempt. You stole it missing a limb, you're חייב. chayav.
Okay, so it's not relative, so how about the middle case? You
stole it with a limb and then you cut off the limb
and then you sold it. Okay, is it relative to the way
it was when you stole it, or is it relative to the
thing that you're actually selling? The thing you're selling you have to
sell fully, or is it that the thing you're selling has to
be the full thing that you stole? Okay, and that would be
the case where you stole it and cut off a limb and
then you sold it. Okay, Rav Pappa loves those questions. Okay, תנו
רבנן, tanu rabbanan, our Rabbis taught: גנב ונתן לאחר וטבח, ganav venatan
leachar vetavach, I stole it and then I gave it to Michael,
I said, "Here Michael, שחוטיה, shechutei, please shecht this for me." Okay,
גנב ונתן לאחר ומכר, ganav venatan leachar umachar, or I stole it
and I gave it to Charlie, and Charlie was my fence, and
I said, "Charlie, you know some people who are interested in some
stolen goods, why don't you sell it for me?" Okay,
גנב והקדיש, ganav vehikdish, okay, or I stole it and I sanctified
it. That's going to be, remember before we said it wasn't an
act of מכירה, mechira, here we're going to call it an act
of מכירה, mechira, we'll get back to that. גנב והקיף, ganav vehikif,
let's say I sold it,
I sold it but I didn't sell it by cash, I sold
it on credit. I sold it to Michael, I said, "Fine, you'll
pay me later." Is that a מכירה? mechira? All of these you're
חייב chayav for all of these things. Okay, גנב והחליף, ganav vehichlif,
or I stole it and then I swapped the cow I stole
for Michael's, I don't know, used car.
Okay, is that a מכירה? mechira? Yes. גנב ונתן מתנה, ganav venatan
matana, here's once you say this last one you don't have to
say the earlier ones. מכירה mechira doesn't even mean מכירה. mechira. Even
if I get nothing in exchange. I stole it and I gave
it as a gift, or maybe that's implicit by הקדש. hekdish. So
certainly if you sell it, if you get it by a swap,
you do it by credit, even if you just give it as
a gift and you don't get anything in exchange, that's included under
the idea of selling, which is a חידוש chiddush I think. גנב
ופרע חובו, ganav upara chovo,
let's say I use it to pay off a debt. So you
know, you could say a gift is at least a new transaction.
It's you know, a debt is money that was already owed. That's
also considered a מכירה. mechira. Okay, גנב
ופרע בהיקיפתו, ganav upara behekpeiso, or I used it to pay off
some store credit that I had. Okay, גנב ושלח סבלונות בבית חמיו.
ganav veshilach sivlonot beveit chamiv. This is also sort of like the
gift. I stole it and I sent it to my father-in-law for
the woman I was betrothed to. You know, you send presents before
the wedding. Okay, so that's like a gift, but it's almost like
a gift that is sort of, you know, there's a societal expectation
that that gift will be given.
Anyway, all those cases, it doesn't matter. You basically transferred ownership of
it, so in all those cases משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. meshalem tashlumei
arba vachamisha. Those are all sales. מאי קמשמע לן? mai kamashma lan?
What's the חידוש chiddush of all this? אשמעינן רישא גנב ונתן לאחר
וטבח דיש שליח לדבר עבירה. ashmienan reisha ganav venatan leachar vetavach deyesh
shaliach lidvar aveira.
This is the idea before about שותפין shutfin when they steal, one
of them can slaughter for the two of them because there's an
idea that you don't have to be the one that slaughters. Somebody
else could slaughter for you in this case. The case of טביחה
ומכירה, tvicha umechira, normally you have to do the עבירה aveira yourself,
but here you've already stolen it. It's just getting deeper into the
sin and therefore somebody else could sell it or slaughter it for
you, and you, not the person who sold it, you would be
חייב. chayav. אף על גב דבכל התורה כולה, af al gav debechol
hatora kula, even though normally we say אין שליח לדבר עבירה, ein
shaliach lidvar aveira, that if somebody does something you're not liable, הכא
יש שליח לדבר עבירה. hacha yesh shaliach lidvar aveira. Here there is.
מאי טעמא? mai taama? What's the reason? וטבחו ומכרו, utvacho umacharo, you
slaughter it and sell it. מה מכירה דלא אפשר דלאו על ידי
אחר, ma mechira dlo efshar dlav al yedei acher, the same way
selling it requires another side, a buyer, אף טביחה על ידי אחר.
af tvicha al yedei acher. Even if you slaughter it through another
person you are liable. This is the principle we saw before and
that's why also when שותפין shutfin steal, if one slaughters for the
two of them you're חייב. chayav. If one slaughters on their own,
they're exempt because it's not slaughtering it fully, as it were.
מחייב. mechayev. ואשמעינן סיפא, vashmienan seifa, and the end. Now that's funny.
The Gemara skips over what I think is all the חידושים chiddushim
that selling doesn't require getting money for it. I would say selling
means you sold it for money. I would say it's a big
חידוש chiddush to say if you gave it as a gift you're
חייב. chayav. That the Gemara doesn't think is a חידוש. chiddush. What
it does think is a חידוש chiddush is גנב והקדיש, ganav vehikdish,
sanctifying it. That that's considered selling. Why is it selling? מה לי
מכר להדיוט מה לי מכר לשמים? ma li machar lehediot ma li
machar lashamayim? What do I care if you sell it to a
lay person or you sell it to heaven,
to God's domain? Of course, the funny thing is we said before
that if you steal it and you sanctify it as a קרבן
korban you're exempt because it's מעיקרא תורא דראובן והשתא תורא דראובן. meikara
tura direuven vehashta tura direuven. So if you look at Tosafot, Tosafot
says what he said before. גנב והקדיש משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. ganav
vehikdish meshalem tashlumei arba vachamisha. Tosafot says כדמפרש מה לי מכר להדיוט
מה לי מכר לשמים ואיירי בקדשי בדק הבית. kidemefareish ma li machar
lehediot ma li machar lashamayim veairi bekodshei bedek habayit. It's when you
gave it as a donation to the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, דלא
שייך למימר מעיקרא תורא דראובן והשתא תורא דראובן. dlo shayach lemeimar meikara
tura direuven vehashta tura direuven. קדשי מזבח. Kodshei Mizbe'ach. It's not like
a קרבן korban what always is considered
yours, שקרבן קאתי לכפר על הבעלים ונשחט לשמו ושם בעליו עליו. shekorban
ka'asei l'chaper al habealim v'nishchat lishmo v'shem be'alav alav.
There, a sacrifice is brought for the owner's sake, on his behalf,
it's identified with the owner. There, it's not considered when you sanctify
it as a קרבן, korban, it's not considered a change of ownership.
Even though it really isn't yours anymore, it's still associated with you.
Whereas when you give it as a donation,
they might put up, people might remember, oh, you donated this lovely,
this lovely cow, but it's no longer considered your cow. The donation
happened in the past. It's now fully the בית המקדש's, Beis HaMikdash
it's not normally associated with you, that is a מכירה. mechira. And
again, the way I framed it is it's not only a question
of whether it's identified, but it's a question of process. When I
give something as a donation, that's like an act of מכירה. mechira.
The idea of giving my cow as a donation to the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash is I am taking it out of my possession,
and I am transferring the title, and giving the title over to
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, they're now the owners. It's about ownership.
קדשי בדק הבית Kodshei Bedek HaBayis is about ownership. קדשי מזבח Kodshei
Mizbe'ach is not a question about who owns my cow that I
just sanctified as an עולה. olah. It's not a process of transferring
ownership. It's process of instilling its קדושה, kedusha, and giving it that
status, and therefore that status is now קדוש kadosh and I'm going
to bring it as a קרבן. korban. Okay, so that's a very
different type of a process and that's not חייב ארבעה וחמישה, chayiv
arba'ah v'chamishah, but קדשי בדק הבית Kodshei Bedek HaBayis is about ownership
and you are חייב ארבעה וחמישה. chayiv arba'ah v'chamishah. So we will
end here.